<!-- Chapter 1 - an introduction to the book -->
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <section id="preface-what">
    <title>What is Synopsis?</title>
    <para>Synopsis is not a random name. Consider this definition:</para>
    <blockquote>
      <attribution>Webster's Revised Unabridged Dictionary, &copy; 1996, 1998 MICRA, Inc.</attribution>
      <para>
        \Syn*op"sis\, n.; pl. Synopses. [L., from Gr. ?; sy`n with, together + ? a
        sight, view, from the root seen in E. optic.] A general view, or a
        collection of heads or parts so arranged as to exhibit a general view of
        the whole; an abstract or summary of a discourse; a syllabus; a
        conspectus.
      </para>
      <para>
        That the reader may see in one view the exactness of the method, as well
        as force of the argument, I shall here draw up a short synopsis of this
        epistle. --Bp. Warburton.
      </para>
      <para>
        Syn: Abridgment; compendium; epitome; abstract; summary; syllabus;
        conspectus. See Abridgment.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      Synopsis is a tool for generating documentation of a program's structure,
      using mainly comments embedded in the source code. The end result is
      ideally documentation that provides an accessible view of the interface,
      structure and workings of a program or library, depending on the intent
      of the person creating the documentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Synopsis has a very modular design, allowing multiple source languages
      and output formats. Between the input and output, complex
      transformations can be made to simplify the structure or rename types,
      as suits the documentation.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="preface-this">
    <title>This Document</title>
    <para>
      This document is intended to be a complete user manual for the Synopsis
      application. It provides both introductory materials on how to use
      the application to generate documentation, and advanced materials on how
      to extend Synopsis with custom modules to perform extra tasks.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="preface-history">
    <title>Document Revision History</title>
    <para>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>Nov 18 2002</date>
        <authorinitials>SD</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Initial version</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    </para>
  </section>
</preface>
<!-- vim: set ts=8 et sts=2 sw=2: -->
